<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>math on fml blog</title>
    <link>https://fml-fam.github.io/blog/tags/math/</link>
    <description>Recent content in math on fml blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://fml-fam.github.io/blog/tags/math/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Matrix Factorizations for Data Analysis</title>
      <link>https://fml-fam.github.io/blog/2020/07/03/matrix-factorizations-for-data-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://fml-fam.github.io/blog/2020/07/03/matrix-factorizations-for-data-analysis/</guid>
      <description>Integers can be factored into products of special kinds of integers with useful properties called primes. Similarly, matrices can be factored into products of special kinds of matrices with useful properties.
Because data analysis often involves operating on numeric matrices, understanding how and why to factor matrices can be very helpful. We&amp;rsquo;re going to talk about the major factorizations, namely LU, Cholesky, QR, SVD, and Eigendecomposition. There are others, but if you master these, then you&amp;rsquo;re off to a great start.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SVD via Lanczos Iteration</title>
      <link>https://fml-fam.github.io/blog/2020/06/15/svd-via-lanczos-iteration/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://fml-fam.github.io/blog/2020/06/15/svd-via-lanczos-iteration/</guid>
      <description>Background Every few years, I try to figure out the Lanczos method to approximate SVD of a rectangular matrix. Unfortunately, every resource I find always leaves out enough details to confuse me. All of the information I want is available across multiple writeups, but everyone uses different notation, making things even more confusing.
This time I finally sat down and got to a point where I finally felt like I understood it.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>